Chapter 10. A warm welcome.
The day grew lighter and warmer as they floated along. After a while, the river
rounded a steep shoulder of land that came down upon their left. Under its
rocky feet like an inland cliff the deepest stream had flowed, lapping and
bubbling. Suddenly the cliff fell away.
The shores sank, the trees ended. Then Bilbo saw a sight. The lands opened wide
about him, filled with the waters of the river, which broke up and wandered in a
hundred winding courses, or halted in marshes and pools, dotted with every
side. But still a strong water flowed on steadily through the midst, and far away
its dark head in a torn cloud. There looms the mountain, its nearest
neighbors to the northeast, and the tumbled land that join it to them could
not be seen. All alone it rose and looked across the marshes to the forest, the lonely mountain.
Bilbo had come far and through many adventures to see it, and now he did not
like the look of it in the least. As he listened to the talk of the raftmen and
pieced together the scraps of information they let fall, he soon
realized that he was very fortunate ever to have seen it at all, even from this
distance. Dreary, as had been his imprisonment, and unpleasant as was his
position, to say nothing of the poor dwarves underneath him. Still, he had
been more lucky than he had guessed. The talk was all of the trade that came and
went on the waterways and the growth of the traffic on the river as the roads
out of the east towards Murkwood vanished or fell into disuse and of the
bickerings of the lakemen and the wood elves about the upkeep of the forest
river and the care of the banks. Those lands had changed much since the days
when dwarves dwelt in the mountain, days which most people now remembered only as
a very shadowy tradition. They had changed even in recent years, and since
the last news that Gandalf had had of them. Great floods and rains had swollen
the waters that flowed east, and there had been an earthquake or two, which
some were inclined to attribute to the dragon alluding to him, chiefly with a
curse, and an ominous nod in the direction of the mountain. The marshes
and bogs had spread wider and wider on either side. Pats had vanished, and many
a rider in wanderer, too, if they had tried to find the lost ways across. The
elfrode through the wood, which the dwarves had followed on the advice of
Bejorn, now came to a doubtful and little used end at the eastern edge of
the forest. Only the river offered any longer a safe way from the skirts of
Mirkwood in the north to the mountain shadowed plains beyond, and the river
was guarded by the wood elves king. So, you see, Bilbo had come in the end by
the only road that was any good. It might have been some comfort to Mr.
Bagdan shivering on the barrels, if he had known that news of this had reached
Gandal far away, and given him great anxiety, and that he was in fact
finishing his other business, which does not come into this tale, and getting
ready to come in search of Thoren's company. But Bilbo did not know it. All
he knew was that the river seemed to go on and on and on forever, and he was
hungry, and had a nasty cold in the nose, and did not like the way the
mountain seemed to frown at him and threaten him as it drew ever nearer.
After a while, however, the river took a more southerntherly course, and the
mountain receded again, and at last, late in the day, the shores grew rocky.
The river gathered all its wandering waters together into a deep and rapid
flood, and they swept along at great speed. The sun had set when turning with
another sweep towards the east. The forest river rushed into the long lake.
There it had a wide mouth with stony cliff-like gates at either side, whose
feet were piled with shingles. The long lake. Bilbo had never imagined that any
water that was not the sea could look so big. It was so wide that the opposite
shores looked small and far, but it was so long that its northerly end, which
pointed towards the mountain, could not be seen at all.
Only from the map did Bilbo know that away up there, where the stars of the
Wayne were already twinkling, the running river came down into the lake
from Dale, and with the forest river filled with deep waters, what must once
have been a great deep rocky valley. At the southern end, the doubled waters
poured out again over high waterfalls, and ran away hurriedly to unknown lands.
In the still evening air, the noise of the falls could be heard like a distant
roar. Not far from the mouth of the forest river was the strange town he
heard the elves speak of in the king's cellars. It was not built on the shore,
though there were a few huts and buildings there, but right out on the
surface of the lake, protected from the swirl of the entering river by a
promontory of rock which formed a calm bay. A great bridge made of wood ran out
to where on huge piles made of forest trees was built a busy wooden town, not
a town of elves, but of men who still dared to dwell here under the shadow of
the distant dragon mountain. They still drove on the trade that came up the
great river from the south and was carted past the falls to their town. But
in the great days of old, when Dale and the North was rich and prosperous, they
had been wealthy and powerful, and there had been fleets of boats on the waters,
and some were filled with gold, and some with warriors and armor, and there had
been wars and deeds which were now only a legend. The rotting piles of a greater
town could still be seen along the shores, when the waters sank in a
drought. But men remembered little of all that, though some still sang old
songs of the dwarf kings of the mountain, Thrower and Thra of the race
of Darin, and of the coming of the dragon, and the fall of the lords of
Dale. Some sang too, that Thrower and Thra would come back one day, and gold
would flow in rivers through the mountain gates, and all that land would
be filled with new song and new laughter. But this pleasant legend did
not much affect their daily business. As soon as the raft of barrels came in,
sightboats rode out from the piles of the town, and voices hailed the raft
steers. Then ropes were cast and oars were pulled, and soon the raft was drawn
out of the current of the forest river, and towed away round the high shoulder
of rock into the little bay of Lake Town. There it was morowed, not far from
the shorewood head of the great bridge.
Soon men would come up from the south and take some of the casks away, and
others they would fill with goods they had brought to be taken back up the
stream to the wood elves home. In the meanwhile, the barrels were left afloat
while the elves of the raft and the boatman went to feast in Lake Town. They
would have been surprised if they could have seen what happened down by the
shore after they had gone and the shades of night had fallen. First of all, a
barrel was cut loose by Bilbo and pushed to the shore and opened.
Groans came from inside, and out crept a most unhappy dwarf. Wet straw was in his
draggled beard. He was so sore and stiff, so bruised and buffeted he could
hardly stand or stumble through the shallow water to lie groaning on the
shore. He had a famished and a savage look like a dog that has been chained
and forgotten in a kennel for a week. It was Thoren, but you could only have told
it by his golden chain, and by the color of his now dirty and tattered sky blue
hood with its tarnished silver tassel.
It was sometime before he would be even polite to the hobbit. "Well, are you
alive or are you dead?" asked Bilbo quite crossly. Perhaps he had forgotten
that he had had at least one good meal more than the dwarves, and also the use
of his arms and legs, not to speak of a greater allowance of air. Are you still
in prison, or are you free? If you want
food, and if you want to go on with this silly adventure, it's yours after all,
and not mine, you had better slap your arms and rub your legs and try and help
me get the others out while there is a chance."
Thorin, of course, saw the sense of this. So after a few more groans, he got
up and helped the hobbit as well as he could. In the darkness, floundering in
the cold water, they had a difficult and very nasty job finding which were the
right barrels. Knocking outside and calling only discovered about six
dwarves that could answer. These were unpacked and helped ashore where they
sat or lay muttering and moaning. They were so soaked and bruised and cramped
that they could hardly yet realize their release or be properly thankful for it.
Dwallan and Balin were two of the most unhappy, and it was no good asking them
to help. Bifur and Bofur were less knocked about and drier, but they lay
down and would do nothing. Feelely and Kelly, however, who were young for
dwarves, and had also been packed more neatly with plenty of straw into smaller
casks, came out more or less smiling, with only a bruise or two, and a
stiffness that soon wore off. I hope I never smell the smell of apples again,
said Feelely. My tub was full of it. To smell apples everlastingly when you can
scarcely move and are cold and sick with hunger is maddening. I could eat
anything in the wide world now for hours on end, but not an apple. With the
willing help of Feelely and Killy, Thoren and Bilbo at last discovered the
remainder of the company and got them out. Poor Fat Bomber was asleep or
senseless. Dory, Nori, Aie, One, and Loin were waterlogged and seemed only
half alive. They all had to be carried one by one and laid helpless on the shore.
Well, here we are, said Doran. And I suppose we ought to thank our stars and
Mr. Baggins. I am sure he has a right to expect it, though I wish she could have
arranged a more comfortable journey.
Still all very much at your service once more, Mr. Baggins. No doubt we shall
feel properly grateful when we are fed and recovered. In the meanwhile, what
next? I suggest Lake Town, said Bilbo.
What else is there? Nothing else could of course be suggested, so leaving the
others, Thoren and Feelely and Killy and the Hobbit went along the shore to the
great bridge. There were guards at the head of it, but they were not keeping
very careful watch, for it was so long since there had been any real need,
except for occasional squables about river tolls. They were friends with the
wood elves. Other folk were far away, and some of the younger people in the
town openly doubted the existence of any dragon in the mountain, and laughed at
the gray beards and gammers, who said that they had seen him flying in the sky
in their young days. That being so, it is not surprising that the guards were
drinking and laughing by a fire in their hut, and did not hear the noise of the
unpacking of the dwarves, or the footsteps of the four scouts. Their
astonishment was enormous when Thor and Oakenshield stepped in through the door.
"Who are you and what do you want?" they shouted, leaping to their feet and
groping for weapons. "Thoren, son of Brain, son of bro, king under the
mountain," said the dwarf in a loud voice, and he looked it in spite of his
torn clothes and draggled hood. The gold gleamed on his neck and waist. His eyes
were dark and deep. I have come back. I wish to see the master of your town.
Then there was tremendous excitement.
Some of the more foolish ran out of the hut as if they expected the mountain to
go golden in the night, and all the waters of the lake turned yellow right
away. The captain of the guard came forward. And who are these? He asked,
pointing to Feelely and Killy and Bilbo.
The sons of my father's daughter, answered Thoren. Fely and Killy of the
race of Duran and Mr. Baggins, who has traveled with us out of the west. "If
you come in peace, lay down your arms," said the captain. "We have none," said
Thorin, "and it was true enough their knives had been taken from them by the
wood elves, and the great sword or crest, too. Bilbo had his short sword
hidden as usual, but he said nothing about that. We have no need of weapons
who return at last to our own is spoken of old. Nor could we fight against so
many. Take us to your master. He is at feast, said the captain. Then all the
more reason for taking us to him, burst in Philly, who was getting impatient at
these somnities. We are worn and famished after our long road, and we
have sick comrades. Now make haste, and let us have no more words, or your
master may have something to say to you.
Follow me, then, said the captain, and with six men about them, he led them
over the bridge, through the gates, and into the marketplace of the town. This
was a wide circle of quiet water, surrounded by the tall piles on which
were built the greater houses, and by long wooden quaz with many steps and
ladders going down to the surface of the lake. From one great hall shown many
lights, and there came the sound of many voices. They passed its doors and stood
blinking in the light, looking at long tables filled with folk. I am Thoren,
son of Thra, son of Thor king, under the mountain. I return, cried Thor in a loud
voice from the door before the captain could say anything. All leaped to their
feet. The master of the town sprang from his great chair, but none rose in
greater surprise than the raftmen of the elves who were sitting at the lower end
of the hall. Pressing forward before the master's table, they cried, "These are
prisoners of our king that have escaped, wandering vagabond dwarves that could
not give any good account of themselves sneaking through the woods and molesting
our people." "Is this true?" asked the master. As a matter of fact, he thought
it far more likely than the return of the king under the mountain, if any such
person had ever existed.
It is true that we were wrongfully way laid by the elven king and imprisoned
without cause as we journeyed back to our own land, answered Thoren. But Lach
nor Bar may hinder the homecoming spoken of old. Nor is this town in the wood
elves round. I speak to the master of the town of the men of the lake, not to
the raftmen of the king. Then the master hesitated and looked from one to the
other. The elven king was very powerful in those parts, and the master wished
for no enmity with him, nor did he think much of old songs, giving his mind to
trade and tolls, to cargos and gold, to cargos and gold, to which habit he owed
his position. Others were of different mind, however, and quickly the matter
was settled without him. The news had spread from the doors of the hall like
fire through all the town. People were shouting inside the hall and outside it.
The keys were thronged with hurrying feet. Some began to sing snatches of old
songs concerning the return of the king under the mountain. That it was Thor's
grandson, not Thor himself, that had come back did not bother them at all.
Others took up the song and it rolled loud and high over the lake. The king
beneath the mountains, the king of carvin stone, the lord of silver
fountains shall come into his own. His crown shall be upholden. His harp shall
be rerung. His hall shall echo golden to songs of your resung.
The woods shall wave on mountains and grasp beneath the sun. His wealth shall
flow in fountains and the rivers golden run. The streams shall run in gladness.
The lakes shall shine and burn. All sorrow fail and sadness at the mountain
king's return. So they sang or very like that. Only there was a great deal more
of it, and there was much shouting as well as the music of hops and of fiddles
mixed up with it. Indeed, such excitement had not been known in the
town in the memory of the oldest grandfather.
The wood elves themselves began to wonder greatly, and even to be afraid.
They did not know, of course, how Thoren had escaped, and they began to think
their king might have made a serious mistake. As for the master he saw, there
was nothing else for it but to obey the general clamor for the moment at any
rate, and to pretend to believe that Thoren was what he said. So he gave up
to him his own great chair and set Philly and Killy beside him in places of
honor. Even Bilbo was given a seat at the high table, and no explanation of
where he came in. No songs had alluded to him, even in the obscurest way, was
asked for in the general bustle. Soon afterwards the other dwarves were
brought into the town amid scenes of astonishing enthusiasm.
They were all doctorred and fed and housed and pampered in the most
delightful and satisfactory fashion. A large house was given up to Thoren in
his company. Boats and rowers were put at their service, and crowds sat outside
and sang songs all day, or cheered if any dwarf showed so much as his nose.
Some of the songs were old ones, but some of them were quite new and spoke
confidently of the sudden death of the dragon and of cargos of rich presence
coming down the river to Lake Town.
These were inspired largely by the master, and they did not particularly
please the dwarves, but in the meantime they were well contented, and they
quickly grew fat and strong again.
Indeed, within a week they were quite recovered, fitted out in fine cloth of
their proper colors, with beards combed and trimmed and proud steps.
Thoren looked and walked as if his kingdom was already regained and smou
chopped up into little pieces.
Then, as he had said, the dwarves good feeling towards the little hobbit grew
stronger every day. There were no more groans or grumbles. They drank his
health, and they patted him on the back, and they made a great fuss of him, which
was just as well, for he was not feeling particularly cheerful. He had not
forgotten the look of the mountain, nor the thought of the dragon, and he had,
besides, a shocking cold. For 3 days he sneezed and coughed, and he could not go
out, and even after that his speeches at banquetss were limited to, "Thank you very much."
In the meanwhile, the wood elves had gone back up the forest river with their
caros, and there was great excitement in the king's palace. I have never heard
what happened to the chief of the guards and the butler. Nothing, of course, was
ever said about keys or barrels while the dwarves stayed in Lake Town, and
Bilbo was careful never to become invisible. Still, I dare say more was
guessed than was known, though doubtless Mr. Baggins remained a bit of a mystery.
In any case, the king knew now the dwarf's errand, or thought he did, and
he said to himself, "Very well. We'll see. No treasure will come back through
Murkwood without my having something to say in the matter, but I expect they
will all come to a bad end, and serve them right." He at any rate did not
believe in dwarves fighting and killing dragons like Smout, and he strongly
suspected attempted burglary or something like it, which shows he was a
wise elf and wiser than the men of the town, though not quite right, as we
shall see in the end. He sent out his spies about the shores of the lake, and
as far northward towards the mountain as they would go, and waited. At the end of
a fortnight, Thoren began to think of departure. While the enthusiasm still
lasted in the town was the time to get help. It would not do to let everything
cool down with delay. So he spoke to the master and his counselors and said that
soon he and his company must go on towards the mountain. Then for the first
time the master was surprised and a little frightened, and he wondered if
Thoren was, after all really a descendant of the old kings. He had
never thought that the dwarves would actually dare to approach Smalow, but
believed they were frauds who would sooner or later be discovered and be turned out.
He was wrong. Thoren, of course, was really the grandson of the king under
the mountain, and there is no knowing what a dwarf will not dare and do for
revenge or the recovery of his own. But the master was not sorry at all to let
them go. They were expensive to keep and their arrival had turned things into a
long holiday in which business was at a standstill. Let them go and bother smog
and see how he welcomes them. He thought certainly Oenthra's son throws son was
what he said. You must claim your own.
The hour is at hand spoken of old. What help we can offer shall be yours, and we
trust to your gratitude when your kingdom is regained.
So one day, although autumn was now getting far on, and winds were cold, and
leaves were falling fast, three large boats left Lake Town, laden with rowers,
dwarves, Mr. Baggins, and many provisions. Horses and ponies had been
sent round by circuitous paths to meet them at their appointed landing place.
The master and his counselors bade them farewell from the great steps of the
town hall that went down to the lake.
People sang on the que and out of windows. The white oes dipped and
splashed, and off they went north up the lake on the last stage of their long
journey. The only person thoroughly unhappy was Bilbo. Chapter 11. On the